We said, "Okay, we're going to go for
AGI." 99% of the world thought we were
crazy. 1% of the world they really
resonated with. You know, in 10 or 20
years, unless something goes hugely
wrong, we'll have like unimaginable
super intelligence. This is the best
time ever in the history of
technology ever, period, to start a
company.
[Music]
Well, Sam, thank you so much for joining
us and thanks for all the inspiration. I
mean, OpenAI itself uh is a true
inspiration for any really really
ambitious person. Um maybe we just start
with that. I mean, what were some of the
decisions early that seemed small that
turned out to be incredibly pivotal? I
mean, just deciding to do it was a big
one. Like there we got very close to not
starting OpenAI. Um AGI sounded crazy. I
was I had Gary's job then and we were
you know there was like all this other
great stuff to do that would work all
these great startups and AGI was like
kind of a pipe dream and also even if it
was possible deep mind seemed like
impossibly far ahead and so we had this
year over the course of 2015 where we
were talking about starting it and you
know it was like kind of coin flippy um
and I think this is the the story of
like many ambitious things where they
seem so difficult and there's such good
reasons not to do them that really takes
a core of people that like sit in a
room, look each other in the eye and
say, "All right, let's do this." Uh, and
those are like very important moments
and I think when in doubt, you should
lean into them. So, there were just a
billion things, a billion reasons why
people might say you shouldn't do it. I
mean, off the bat, like even you one of
the things you figured out was the
scaling laws. It's so hard to remember
what it was like. Uh, next year will be
our 10 year anniversary and so not not
Yeah. Thank you.
But to to like remember what the vibes
were like about AI 10 years ago, that
was like way before the first language
models that worked. We were trying to
like play video games and we had this
little robotic hand that could sort of
barely do a Rubik's cube and we had no
ideas for products, no revenue, no
really idea that we were ever going to
have revenue. And we were like sitting
around at conference tables and
whiteboards trying to come up with ideas
for papers to write. It it was such it's
it's like hard to explain now because it
looks so obvious now how improbable it
seemed at the time and how the idea of
chatbt was like completely in the realm
of science fiction. I mean, one of the
things that really jumped out at me was
uh you sort of, you know, rallied this
idea that you should be working on AGI
and then simultaneously you found the
smartest people in the world who were
working on that thing. That second part
was sort of easier than it sounds. If if
you say we're going to like do this
crazy thing and it's and it's exciting
and it's important if it works and other
people aren't doing it, you can actually
like get a lot of people together. Um,
and so we were we said, "Okay, we're
going to go for AGI." 99% of the world
thought we were crazy. 1% of the world
that really resonated with. Turned out
there were a lot of smart people in that
1% and you could get like there wasn't
really anywhere else for them to go. So
we were able to really concentrate the
talent and it was a mission that people
cared about. So even though it seemed
unlikely, if it worked, it it seemed
super valuable. And
we've observed this many times with
startups. If you are doing the same
thing as everyone else, it is very hard
to concentrate talent and it's very hard
to get people to like really believe in
a mission. And if you're doing like a
oneofone thing,
uh you you have a really nice tailwind
there. Okay. So, some people in this
room might be thinking like, should I
try to start an OpenAI scale thing off
the bat? Uh you know, you you also
worked on Loop your first time around.
You know, were there lessons from that?
OpenAI was not an open eye scale thing
off the bat. OpenAI was like eight
people in a room and then it was 20
people in a room and it was very unclear
what to do and we were just like trying
to write a good research paper. Um
so the the things that eventually become
really big do not start off that way. I
think it's important to like dream that
it could be big if it works. Nothing big
starts that way. and and and
Venode Kla has this quote that I've
always liked which is there's a very big
difference between a Z million dollar
startup and a zero billion dollar
startup
but they both have zero dollars of
revenue. They're both like a few people
sitting in a room and you're both trying
to they're both just trying to get the
first thing to work. Um, so the only the
only advice I have about trying to start
something big is pick pick a market
where it seems like there's some version
of the future where it could be big if
it works. But other than that, it's like
one dumb foot in front of the other for
a long time. How people use chatd has
changed a lot. How people use your API
has changed a lot. Uh, what surprises
you the most with the latest models like
03 and what emergent behaviors or use
cases are standing out to you right now?
I think we're in a really interesting
time. We haven't been in one of these
for a while. Uh but like right now we're
in an interesting time where the the
product overhang relative to what the
models like what the models are capable
of is here the products that people have
figured out to build is way down here.
There's a huge even if the models got no
better which of course they will uh
there's a huge amount of new stuff to
build. And also like last week 03 cost
five times as much as it did this week
and that's going to keep going. I think
people will be astonished at how much
the price per performance falls. Um we
have an open source model coming out
soon. I think people are going to be
Yeah,
I don't want to like steal the team's
glory and pre-announce this, but I think
you all will be astonished. I think it
will be like much better than you're
hoping for and the ability to like use
it to run incredibly powerful models
locally is gonna like really really
surprise people on what's possible. Um
but so you have this world where like
the model capability has gone into like
a kind of new like a very new realm. Um
the cost of the APIs are going to keep
falling quite dramatically. the open
source models are going to be super
great and I think we have not yet seen
the level of new product innovation that
the reasoning models are capable of
which makes sense they're pretty new but
this is like an exceptional time to go
build a company that takes advantage of
this sort of new thing that exists this
sort of new square on a periodic table
that no one has built with yet. So only
in the last month I think have we really
started to see startups that are saying
okay like reasoning models are different
you know the whole interaction model is
different and really building for that.
I mean for me even memory has turned
into it feels like I'm talking to
someone who knows me which is
interesting. Yeah me memory is my
favorite feature that we've launched
this year. I don't think most people at
open air would say that because and
we've launched a lot of stuff but I love
memory and chatbt. Um and I think it
points to where we will hopefully go
with the product which is you will have
this like entity that gets to know you
that connects to all your stuff and that
is like proactively helping you. It'll
it won't just be like you send a message
and it sends you one back. But it'll
like be running all the time. It'll be
looking at your stuff. It'll know when
to send you a message. It'll know when
to go do something on your behalf.
you'll have, you know, special new
devices and it'll be integrated on every
other service you use and you'll just
have this thing running with you
throughout your life. I think memory is
the first time where people can sort of
see that coming. Uh, back in the day you
tweeted a little bit about uh her where,
you know, when is that coming? Can you
give us an alpha leak around that? I
think gradually is the answer. No, no.
If I had a date in mind, I would
probably just be excited and tell you.
Um, but like it's a little bit here with
memory, right? It'll be a little more
here when it's persistently running in
the background and sending you stuff.
It'll be a lot more here when we ship
the first new device. Um, but I think
the key of her is not the little piece
of hardware. It's that this thing
got to a point where it could run in the
background and feel like a sort of AI
companion. I guess we're starting to see
um the power of LMS with integrations
into your real data. Uh, you know, I've
heard rumors that MCP is coming to
OpenAI. I think today. Yeah. Oh, today.
I think so. Fantastic.
What has been surprising about the
actual integrations? Like have you been
seeing people actually operating on
their core database? You know, at YC we
actually have that agent infrastructure
internally and we use it all the time.
Definitely people are starting to use
chatbt as this like operating system
with everything with their whole lives
in it. Um and integrating into as many
data sources as possible is important.
um devices that are always with you,
like new kinds of web browsers, the
connection to all data sources, memory,
and then a model that's persistently
running. You put all that together, I I
think you get to like a pretty powerful
place. Do you think that'll be in the
cloud in the future, or will it be on
our desktop or some mix of both? Some
mix of all of that. Definitely people
will run local models for some things
like man, if we could push like half the
chatbt workload onto your local devices,
no one would be happier than us. like
our cloud. We I think we will run the
like largest and most expensive piece of
infrastructure in the world pretty soon.
So, if we could push some of that off,
that'd be great. Um, but a lot of it
will run on the cloud. Is it surprising
to you how hard it is to get compute? I
mean, we've gotten really good at it,
but it is
we we went from like a
no a zero like no chatbt.com didn't
exist two and a half years ago to like
the fifth biggest website in the world.
It'll be the third at some point,
hopefully someday the first if our
current growth rates continue. And I
think doing that is just hard no matter
what. Like that's you usually get longer
than we've gotten to to scale up a like
infrastructure to for a new company. But
you know, there's like a lot of people
that want to help. Well, it's incredible
incredible work that you guys have been
doing. Um, we're seeing reasoning models
like 03 and 04 mini uh evolve in
parallel with multimodal models like 40.
What happens when these two threads
converge? And what's the vision for GPT5
and beyond? I mean, we we we won't get
all the way here with GPT5, but
eventually we do want one integrated
model that can like reason when it needs
to and generate like real-time video
when it needs to do that. If you ask a
question, you could imagine it thinking
super hard, doing some research, writing
a bunch of code just in time for like a
brand new app only for you to use or
kind of like rendering live video that
you can interact with. Um, so I think
that will feel like
a real new kind of computer interface.
that AI sort of somewhat already does,
but when we get to a model that has like
true complete multimodality, like
perfect video, perfect coding,
everything and deep reasoning, that will
that will feel like quite powerful. It
seems like that might be a hop step over
to the uh embodied aspect. You know,
that's having vision, having speech, and
having reasoning is a hop step to, you
know, yeah, basically the robot we want.
our our our strategy has been nail that
first um and then make sure we can
connect that to a robot. But the time
for the robot is coming soon. Um I think
I am very excited about a world where
when you sign up for like the highest
tier of the chatbt subscription, we send
you a free humanoid robot too. I mean
that future is going to be pretty wild
being able to have robots that do real
work in the real world. I think we're
not that far away now. uh the mechanical
engineering of robots is been quite
difficult uh and and the sort of AI for
the cognitive part has been quite
difficult too but it feels within grasp
um and I think in a few years robots
will
start to do super useful stuff making a
billion robots is still going to take a
while but I don't know I'm interested in
the question of how many robots do you
need to fully automate the supply chain
like if you make a million humanoid
robots the oldfashioned way can they run
the entire supply chain
drive the mining equipment like drive
the container ships run the you know
foundaries and make the new robots and
then maybe like you actually can get a
lot of robots in the world quickly but
the demand for human robots in the world
will be far more than we know how to
think about with the current supply
chain. I guess uh when you were sitting
in my seat, one of the things you led
was uh you know a lot more investment
into hard tech at YC. Um sitting here
where we are geopolitically,
you know, what what do we need to do to
make sure that America can actually have
manufacturing in industrial capacity,
you know, we can't even build precision
screws and large sheet metal without
crazy cost overruns. You know, how what
can we do to make sure that happens
here? There are all of these answers
that people throw around and have thrown
around the same things for a while and
it clearly hasn't worked. So, uh I think
all of the policy is worth trying, but
my instinct is we need to try something
new. We shouldn't keep trying the same
failed stuff. And you know, like AI and
robotics does give us a new possibility
of a way to bring manufacturing back
here and to bring sort of these complex
industries here in a really important
new way. And I would say that's at least
worth trying. Yeah.
um what does defensibility look like
here? You know, one of the classic
questions is, you know, how do I uh
start a startup that doesn't get run
over by Open AI? That's sort of the
number one question that's in our chat.
We don't want to run you over. Um
look, we're going to do our thing
hopefully very well. We are going to try
to make the best super assistant out of
Chat GBT that we can. we're gonna add
the things that we think we need to add
to that. Um, but that is like one small
part of the opportunity in front of us.
And it makes us sad when people are
like, I'm going to start a new startup
and I'm going to like make a version of
Chaz GBT because we think we're going to
do that pretty well and we have like,
you know, kind of a big head start, but
there is so much more space to go after
and there are so many incredible other
companies that have been built using our
platform. Um, we would like to make it
easier for you all. We would like to do
more things like finally now you can
imagine that chat GPT could drive a lot
of traffic to new startups and that
there's like a new kind of app or agent
or whatever you want to call it store
that we could do inside of ChatgPT and
drive traffic to new startups to help.
You could imagine that we could do like
a signin with OpenAI and people could
bring their, you know, personalized
model and easily connect it to a new
startup and that would probably help in
a bunch of ways. Um so we want to be a
platform for other people to build
stuff. Our advice is like don't build
our core
you know chat assistant. Um but there is
another problem which is
and this is the same for every every
kind of like moment that I've seen in
startup history. People get excited
about the same thing at the same time.
And so rather than go build the thing
that you have thought of that is not
everybody what else is doing, we are
like very social creatures and we get
very influenced by what other people are
doing. And I bet if Gary listed off the
five ideas that he hears most often of
what people want to build with AI, like
half the room would raise their hands
for working on one of those five. and
and the I there is hopefully in this
room um the person who's going to start
a company that is like much bigger than
OpenAI someday and I would bet that
person is not working on any of the
five. So it is hard to build something
defensible if everybody else is trying
to do the same thing. Sometimes it
works. It's not impossible. But the best
the most enduring companies are usually
not doing the same thing as everybody
else. And that gives you time to figure
out what the great product is, how to
build the technology before you have to
answer the defensibility question. It
took us a long time to figure out how to
answer the defensibility question for
CHBT. Um, we had built this thing and
for a long time the only defensibility
was like we had the only product out in
the market. Um, and then we kind of like
be a brand that started to be wellknown
and now we have things like memory and
connections, a whole bunch of other
stuff that really is defensible. But you
know that was like a fair criticism of
us for a long time. We didn't have any
defensibility strategy. We just like had
the only good thing out there and then
you have some window before which you
have to build defensibility. One of the
things we've talked about in the past is
that uh we both are big followers of uh
Peter Teal in that he talks a lot about
being contrarian but right. Um
I think that you've Peter is a genius.
Absolutely. And you found you've been
contrarian in really fundamental ways. I
mean going back you know to the
beginning of the conversation people
thought oh this idea that the scaling
laws are valuable today it's you know
taken as basic truth but it was exactly
the opposite of ground truth not that
many years ago when you got that push
back you know what did you and your team
feel did you say you know fui I won't do
what you tell me you know I'm going I'm
going to push back against you know
getting push back means that this is a
contrarian area and we're going to bet
here and we're going to be right. It is
hard to have conviction in the face of a
lot of other people telling you you're
wrong. And I think people who don't who
say it's easy are not being honest. It
gets easier over time. Um but like I
remember one time I can say this one
because it got publicized um in early
not early a few years into OpenAI where
Elon sent us this really mean email.
we've been working together for a while
and said we had a zero% chance of
success. Like not zero. Zero that we
were totally failing. We had showed him
like GPT1 recently. He was like, "This
is crap. It's not gonna work. Doesn't
make sense." And I was really a hero of
mine at the time. And I remember going
home that night and being like, "What if
he's right? Like this sucks."
You know, you're working so hard on this
thing. Like you're pouring your life
force into it. And you have these people
who are smart and that you look up to
and they say, "You are totally wrong."
um or you know
this is just not never going to work or
you don't have defensibility, someone's
going to kill you, this is going to
happen, that's going to happen. And
I don't have a magic answer other than
it's really tough and it gets
significantly easier over time, but it's
going to happen to all of you and you
just like get knocked down and get back
up and brush yourself off and try to
keep going. Let's talk uh AI agents. you
know, that's uh sort of level three AGI.
Uh this is the year I think Greg
Brockman talked about recently. This is
the year of the agent. Um
with tools like operator code
interpreter, what kind of workflows do
you think will disappear uh or appear
that we just aren't ready for yet? For a
long time, chatb was like a Google
replacement. You could ask it something
that was about as long as a Google
query. you know, maybe like half an hour
worth of Google queries it could
assemble together. And that was still
pretty good, but it didn't it it it
still felt like a more advanced version
of search.
But now you start to see things where
you can like really give a task to
codeex for example um or to deep
research and you have this thing go off
and do a bunch of stuff and come back to
you with like a proposal. It's it's like
a very junior employee that can work on
something for like a short period of
time. And if you think about how much of
the work that the world does is work
that can be done in front of a computer
in like few hour chunks where you then
have someone say like okay that was good
enough or not. It's quite a lot. So I I
think this is going to go this is part
of that overhang we were talking about
earlier but I think this is going to go
quite far and I think with current 03 to
say nothing of our next model you can
build a lot of experiences like this.
How do you see the future of human
computer interaction and interfaces and
what are sort of the limitations of
those interfaces that you know motivated
you? You know, one of the things that I
think sci-fi got right is
the idea of the interface almost melts
away. Like voice interfaces today we
think of as something that is kind of
sucky because they don't work that well.
But in theory, if you could say to a
computer, "This is exactly what I want
to happen today. and if there's any
changes, if like I'm delayed, if you
know something happens, I trust you to
like go off and do all those things, but
like I don't want to be interrupted. I
don't want to think about it. Um, and it
just did it all and you trusted that it
worked.
That would be an interface that almost
melted away except when it, you know,
was like a super great human assistant
needed to talk to you. But you would be
like really thrilled. When I like use my
phone today, I feel like I am like
walking down Time Square in New York
getting like bumped into by people. I
love my phone. It's an incredible piece
of technology, but it's like
notification here, this thing happening,
you know, this thing popping up, like
bright colors, like all kinds of
flashing things in me. It's just
stressful.
And I can imagine an interface where the
computer mostly melts away. It does the
stuff I need. Um, but I really trust
that it's going to do a great job of
like surfacing information to me, making
judgment calls about when not to, acting
on my behalf when it should. Uh, and I'm
I'm quite excited for that. Uh, I'm not
going to like tell you what the new
device is. Well, I'll tell you like
one-on-one, but I'm not going to tell
the room, but it's very like I I hope I
hope we can sort of like show people a
different way to have computers. Is that
one of the reasons why you brought on
one of the greatest living designers on
the planet, John, in Johnny Ivan, IO?
Yeah, he he is he is amazing. Um, he is
he really lives up to all the hype. I I
think we've only had kind of two big
revolutions in computer interfaces
really in the last like 50 years. So we
had the you know keyboard and mouse and
screen and then we had touch and phones
and the opportunity to do a new one
doesn't come along that often and I
think AI really does totally open the
playing field for something completely
new and I think if you got to pick one
person to bet on to figure that out he
is the obvious bet. Yeah. So one of the
things that uh we've been debating at YC
that you know don't know if this is good
might be scary for a lot of software
engineers who want to create B2B SAS is
this idea that uh what if in the future
you had your you know underlying
database you have an API layer that is
uh you know your access control and
enforces your business logic and then
the interface is the LLM like your
computer is literally you know the agent
and uh you have just in time software.
They're like complex flows. You're just
going to go in and it'll code gen an
artifact or, you know, a pain for you
that like does that thing you wanted and
it'll go in the file and it'll bring it
back if you ever need it. That's going
to happen. Yeah. Look here here there
are two ways you can look at this. Uh
first of all, assume you all are like
starting startups or have started
startups, think about starting startups.
This is the best time ever in
the history of technology ever, period,
to start a company. Um yeah, this is
uh and but part of the reason it's the
best is because like the ground is
shaking and it's true there are a lot of
these challenges. So on one hand you can
look at something like that and say we
have been a you know SAS company and now
like all of the code can just be
generated right in time when someone
needs it and what does that mean for us
or you can look at it and say wow this
is going to happen but it's going to
happen to everybody and the way startups
win is
when they can iterate faster than big
companies and they can do it at a much
lower cost. like big companies have a
lot of advantages but they iterate very
slowly um and
they you know if something is like very
cheap then a lot of their big advantages
go away. So you can look at this all of
these problems one way or another. But
the way I would recommend looking at
them is everybody is going to face the
same challenges and opportunities. But
when the clock cycle of the industry
changes this much startups almost always
win and we've probably never seen it
change this much. Act on it from that
direction. I think you'll be in
incredible shape. maybe you can invite
me sometime to do a talk about like what
the areas of defensibility that you can
build over time are because I think that
is the inherent question. people are
like, "Oh, okay. You know, I'm a SAS
company. There's going to be just in
time software." I think the question
behind the question is like, "What are
actual defensibility strategies?" So,
that would be a fun talk someday, I
guess. Uh you know, backstage at one of
the last events we had uh you know, we
were talking about the this there's this
book that's sort of like the classic
Mckenzie, which is the seven powers. And
uh I was just thinking about that like I
never would have thought like the two of
us technologists sitting around actually
citing uh a book that you know Mackenzie
consultants are known for. Feels so
wrong. Yeah. I don't know aesthetically
it feels terrible but yes
seven powers. I guess we're entering
this age of intelligence. I love uh that
essay of yours. What do you think this
era will mean for you know how we live
uh how we work and how do we create
value for each other as a society?
You know, in some sense, the the whole
arc of technology is one story, which is
we discover more science, build better
tools, all of society like builds the
scaffolding a little bit higher. Um, and
we we have this more impressive tool
chain. And the whole point of it is that
one person can do way more than they
could before.
And this has been going on for a long
long time. each generation. Uh certainly
I mean if you compare a person today
from a person 100 or thousand years ago,
one person is incredibly more capable
and the kind of like social contract is
that you put something, you know, you
build the next layer of scaffolding. But
what someone can do now with this new
set of tools, with this, you know, this
new layer that's been built in is pretty
incredible. And
I think the
one of the things that will feel most
different about
these next 10 years versus these last 10
years is how much a single person or a
small group of people with a lot of
agency can get done. And that is a
bigger deal than it sounds like u
because coordination costs are are huge.
And when we can empower people with more
knowledge, more tools, more resources,
whatever,
I think we won't just see like a little
bit more stuff get built, but because of
these kind of coordination costs across
people, we'll see like a real stuff
change. So I think the the amount that
one person or small team get done, the
satisfaction in doing that and and most
importantly like the quality of stuff
we'll all get for each other will be
quite remarkable. When I think back
about the OpenAI story, I often think
about just the kind of
key few tens of people that did the
amazing work that led to what we all
have now. But I try to remember that I
always also have to think about like the
tens of millions of people, maybe it's
more uh throughout history that started
like digging rocks out of the ground,
figuring out how semiconductors work,
building computers, building the
internet, and on and on and on that let
this small group be able to work at such
a high level of impact that they never
would have been able to do without the
collective output of society.
Is it surprising to you to what degree?
I mean, this room is you're preaching to
the room of the converted, but uh this
is awesome, by the way. I mean, this is
like the collected set of people who are
going to go create the future, but um
there's, you know, yeah, there's there's
maybe like never been a gathering like
this in one place before. This is this
is very cool to see. But at the same
time, you know, we're in some ways, uh,
this is the leading cutting edge of all
of society because there are seven and a
half billion people who probably h, you
know, have not even tried this stuff
yet. And not only that, their main
interaction with it is uh, that it
doesn't work, that it hallucinates.
You know, what what do you have to say
to the 3,000 people in front of you
right now? Just this is the the thin
edge of the spear. We are literally
teaching people and giving people this
technology. First of all, that's like a
great place to be in. Um, one of the one
of the most fun things about working at
YC is you get to like live on the
leading edge and you get to be around
the people who are the advanced guard.
Um, and that's just like a fun way to
live your life and you get to see what's
coming and, you know, hopefully have
some small amount of input into shaping
it. Uh,
but I don't know. I think AI is like
somewhat mainstream right now. I the the
the negative the way that it's not is
most people still think of AI as chat
GPT and a lot of people use chat GPT but
they use it like a a chatbot and they
have not yet wrapped their head around
what's what's coming next and probably
you all have but
I don't know it's like a great privilege
to get to live a little bit in the
future and uh you know go build stuff
for everybody else coming along. So,
you're sort of one of the best people in
the world at um bringing together the
smartest people. Um what are some of the
hardest lessons you've had to learn
about hiring? A lot of the people in
this room like they have never managed a
person before, let alone gotten someone
to quit their, you know, six to seven
figure job at some big company to come
work on their revolution. hiring really
smart people who are clearly really
driven and really productive and can
work as part of a team I think does get
you
90% of the way there and the degree to
which people focus on other things to
hire for always surprises me. So I think
you know given that we can't do the full
45 minutes right now really smart people
driven curious self-motivated
hardworking
uh like good track record of
accomplishment and can work really well
as part of a team and sort of aligned
with the company's vision and so
everybody's at least going for the same
the same direction that works pretty
well. I mean by uh strong track record
do you mean the person who's like you
know sort of been an administrator and
had like the the you know top name at
the top institution for 20 years or do
you mean like because you you went the
other way? I
I don't especially early in a startup I
don't believe in hiring those people.
There experience is valuable and there
are times where you you really need that
but I have not had success and to be
frank like YC has not had that much
success trying to start with like the
very senior eminent administrator as one
of the like you know as the first hire
in a startup. Um I would I would take
like young scrappy
but clearly like get stuff done um over
the person who has like the extremely
polished track record. There will come a
time where you need some of those people
later. But I don't know how you do it,
but when I when I was like reading YC
applications, I would like never look at
the resume items. You know, you worked
at like Google or went to this college.
I never cared. I would always go right
to like what's the most impressive stuff
you've done? And then sometimes I would
like not be convinced by that and go
look at the resume. But that was always
like a backup to me as a secondary
thing. So sort of look look at what
they've actually what they've coded,
what they've built, like their velocity,
how they think about problems and solve
them. I see PB back there. He has this
quote, I hope it's his quote because
I've attributed to him a bunch of times
of hire for slope, not y intercept. And
I think that's just like unbelievably
great advice. Let's talk about um being
CEO of OpenAI. What are some of the
hardest lessons there just overall? I
don't recommend it. Um,
no one single challenge would be that
hard, but the number of things we have
to do at the same time and the kind of
like number of other big companies that
are gunning for us in various ways, it's
just like more context than I thought it
was possible to handle at once and more
sort of like switching from like big big
decision to like totally unrelated but
also huge decision. Looking ahead 10 to
20 years, what are you sort of most
personally
excited about? You know, and what should
uh people be building now to make that
future possible? You know, there are
people who are scientists, there are
people who are software engineers, there
are people who are I mean this is an all
technical crowd.
Look, there there's a lot um you know,
in 10 or 20 years, unless something goes
hugely wrong, we'll have like
unimaginable super intelligence. And I'm
very excited to see how that goes.
Forced to pick one thing to just not
leave it as like a vague answer. Um I
think AI for science is what I'm
personally most excited about. I I am a
believer that to a first order
approximation all long-term sustainable
economic growth in the world like
everything that leads to people's lives
getting better um is basically
discovering new science and having
reasonably good governance and
institutions so that that science can
get developed and shared with the world.
But if we could vastly increase the rate
of new scientific discovery with AI, uh
I believe that would compound to just
incredible increases and wonders for
everyone's lives. So I think I'd pick
that on that time frame. I guess uh one
of the things I've been always really
impressed by is uh you know you were you
you know personally recruited Helon to
come do Y Combinator and uh they're
doing incredible things over on the
Fusion side. Um, was that something that
you were thinking about even all the way
back then or you know obviously energy
and climate was sort of a part of uh,
you know, what everyone's worried about
even back then. But this is a little bit
embarrassing. I've been obsessed with
energy and AI as like the two the things
that I thought would be the two most
important things or at least the ones I
was going to be most that I felt most
passionate about for a long time. and
and really like the two areas that I I
knew I wanted to like concentrate time
and capital towards. I I cannot recall
ever thinking until like after starting
Open AI that they were going to be so
obviously related
that you know that that energy would be
the eventually the fundamental limiter
on how much intelligence we could have.
And I don't know how I missed that
because I usually am good at thinking
about things like that but I I really
did think of them as like very
independent. you know, we were going to
need AI to have all the ideas, energy to
make all the stuff happen in the world.
And I obviously right after starting
open AI, I got obsessed with meaning
energy for AI. But like pre205, I think
I thought of them as orthogonal vectors.
I mean, you I'm sure you've seen that
chart that um you know, all the
effective accelerationists in the room
have seen around basically having a high
standard of living like the sort of
really it's I'm obsessed with this
chart. I've been obsessed with that
chart a long time. um it's directly uh
related to the amount of energy that any
given person has access to. Yeah. I I
think this is one of the most amazing
charts over a long like long long period
of human history is the correlation of
quality of life and abundance of energy
and cost of energy. So that was that
chart and charts like that were a
significant reason that I got obsessed
with energy in the first place. It it is
it is just this like crazy high impact
thing. It sounds like it wasn't entirely
uh interdependent. It was more you had
twin interest, but you've literally
woven them together. I had like the one
interest of like radical abundance and
just like what what what were the kind
of technological leverage points to just
like make the future like wildly
different and better and these is the
two kind of key things for that. But not
as not as much as the same vector. Now I
think a lot about like how much energy
can we actually build on Earth before we
just heat the planet too much from
running the GPUs and like how long can
we go before we have to put all the GPUs
in space. Um but at the time yeah I
really thought of them differently. I
mean it seems like one of the uh
defining beliefs that technologists uh
uniquely ideally have that they believe
that we can actually create that sort of
abundance. You know, if you have
intelligence on tap and then you have
energy on tap, then um how does that go?
It's like, you know, all uh all watched
over by machines of loving grace. I I've
never been to one of those deg
conferences in Europe or whatever. Um
but I've always kind of wanted to go to
one. This is the anti-dgrowth. This is
the anti-drowth conference. Totally. But
I would like love to be like sitting,
you know, in the dark in the cold with
no one pulling out their phones and just
like talking about how horrible
everything was and there was no hope.
Like I would love to experience that
mindset once because I've never felt it.
Um, and I think it is like it it is one
of the movements that has been ever
hardest for me to identify with.
Obviously, this is like my crew and my
world, but the the sort of like the
optimism of startups of San Francisco,
of the technology industry, of AI, of
what all y'all y'all will do, uh like
that is that is like the natural space
my brain abides and it's very hard for
me to really empathize with the other
side of that, but I'm pretty sure we're
right and they're wrong. How do we get
there though, right? you this incredible
vision of technology actually creating
for abundance for others. I mean you've
already done so much but you know point
us the way like you know how how else do
we get there? How do we make it faster?
You know does government play a role in
this? Almost just about five years ago
like pretty much this week we put GPT3
into an API and people started playing
with it and it was barely usable. It was
quite embarrassing. Um and in five years
we have gone from this like thing that
could barely write a sentence to a thing
that is like you know PhD level
intelligence in most areas. Um five more
years I think we'll be able to maintain
the same rate of progress. And I think
if we do that if we also build out the
infrastructure to serve that to people
then everybody in this room will figure
out how to take that technology and
adapt it to what everybody needs. The
the analogy I like most for AI is the
transistor like the historical tech
technical analogy. You know, some people
figured out like a new really important
scientific discovery
and society, the economy, whatever you
want to call it, just got to work, just
did its thing. The magic of that just
figured out how to make incredible value
for people and really over a fairly
short period of decades significantly
ramp up quality of life. I think this
will be even faster and steeper than
that. But I think it'll go in
directionally the same way. You know, we
need to make the great technology,
figure out the remaining scientific
stuff, which I don't think there's much
left. We need to figure out how to build
out the infrastructure
that you all will need to be able to
service and then you all have got to go
figure out what what people in the world
need um with this new magic. So, let's
uh flash back to 2005. Uh the very first
batch of Y Combinator. Um, how did you
hear about Paul Graham? You were reading
his essays. I was reading his essays.
So, I'd heard about like he kind of had
this cult following on the internet, but
I heard about uh what was then called
the summer founders program and now it's
just called Y Cominator from Blake Ross
who I lived in the same freshman dorm
with and posted about it on Facebook.
And then um I think Paul said, "Oh,
you're a freshman. You know that there's
like another batch coming." And what did
you reply to him by email with? You
know, funny you bring that up. I just
dug up the email like a couple of days
ago because I I felt I had been misqued
over time. I'm curious. And
the the his telling of the story is I
said like I'm a sophomore and I'm
coming. But I wrote a much nicer thing
than that. It was like oh maybe there
was some misunderstanding. You know,
actually I'm a sophomore and I can still
make it and I would like love to if
that's still okay to come the next day.
So I in some ways you know the wild
thing is you're sitting in front of uh
3,000 people who kind of was you know
they they are sitting where you were
back in 2005. Um what would you say to
you know the Sam Alman from that time
you know given what you know all the
things you've seen all the things you've
learned since like what are the things
that you're most surprised you didn't
know that I mean it just took I mean
you've been through it you know like
you've you've done it. I wish someone
had like taught me the importance of
like conviction and
resilience over a long period of time.
People don't really talk about how hard
that is. it's like easy for a little
while, but your reserves kind of like
wear down on it and how to how to keep
that going for a long period of time.
Um,
also just sort of like trust that it's
eventually going to work out. Like
obviously my first startup didn't work
that well. Um, I think a lot of people
kind of give up after one failed
startup, but startups don't work out all
the time. Uh, and learning how to keep
going through that, keep working through
that is is I think really important.
Developing like trust in your own
instincts and increasing that trust as
you refine your decision-making and
instincts over time. I think that's
really important. Kind of courage to
work on stuff that is out of fashion but
is what you believe and what you care
about. Uh, I think that's really
important. I had a kid recently and the
thing everyone tells you when you have a
kid is that it is the best thing you
will ever do but also it is the hardest
thing you will ever do. Like the the
good parts are much better than you can
imagine. Um the hard parts are much
harder. That is all totally true. And
that is also basically what I feel like
being an entrepreneur is like the good
parts are really great better than you
think and the hard parts are like
shockingly much harder than anyone can
can express in a way that uh makes any
sense to you and you have to just keep
going. Sam Alman. Everyone, thank you.
Thank you.